Finding Aid for George William Moore papers, 1859-1956
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George William Moore papers1859-1956
Moore, George William, b. 1847-1926.
1 oversize folders
5 oversize volumes
7 linear feet
07167 Aa 2; UAm
Detroit attorney and businessman; active in the Michigan Democratic Party and a strong supporter of and personal correspondent with William Jennings Bryan. Collection includes correspondence, clippings, and financial records related to Moore, his family, and his estate; the law firm of Moore & Moore; and associated business interests..
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was donated to the library by Jasper L. Moore (donor no. 9964 ) in October 2007 and January 2010.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
George William Moore was born in Auburn Township, Michigan in 1847 to George Washington and Mary (Emory) Moore, the second youngest of six children (Francis, James, Eliza (Monroe), and Mary (Miller)). He received his early education in Romulus, attended seminary in Ypsilanti, and in 1872 was graduated from the University of Michigan and admitted to the bar. That same year he co-founded the firm of Moore & Moore with his friend and classmate, George Whitney Moore and commenced his legal practice. Despite their political differences (George Whitney Moore was a Republican who was elected to the Michigan House of Representatives in 1878), the two remained lifelong friends and shared equally in expenses and profits of the firm until George Whitney Moore's death in 1915.
George William Moore married Katherine De Mill, the daughter of prominent Detroit businessman Peter E. De Mill and a cousin of Governor William Comstock, in a lavish ceremony in 1885 and they had a daughter, Katherine Palmer Moore, in 1888. The couple lived largely separate lives after the turn of the century and divorced in 1922. Two years later Katherine married Daniel J. Campau Jr., a close friend and business associate of George, who remained a bachelor for the rest of his life.
Although George William Moore never stood for political office, he was actively involved in the Michigan Democratic Party and was a staunch supporter of William Jennings Bryan in his presidential bids of 1896, 1900, and 1908. Moore was a member of a district branch of the State Central Committee (the ruling body of the Michigan's Democratic party) and his close friend Daniel J. Campau was the Michigan Democratic State Chair. Moore actively campaigned for candidates, maintained correspondence with various political figures, and also wrote and published political pamphlets on the American monetary system and foreign affairs.
The firm of Moore & Moore practiced constitutional, commercial, and civil law and engaged in real estate, loans, and various business endeavors. George William Moore himself was heavily involved in land, mining, and manufacturing enterprises with his family (his brother, Francis M. Moore, was a deputy clerk for the U.S. District Court in Marquette and a distinguished businessman in the Upper Peninsula) and an array of associates throughout the U.S. The Moore family was among the principles of the Barnes Land Company, which leased land to the Cleveland Cliffs Iron Mining Company that was the site of the infamous Barnes-Hecker Mine tragedy 1926, the worst mining accident in Michigan's history. Moore remained active in his various business pursuits up to his death in 1926..
The George William Moore papers provide a complex view of life in Michigan in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. Correspondence from the family home in Van Buren Township documents rural concerns and daily activities, while deeds and correspondence from the Upper Peninsula detail the explosive growth of land and mining interests in the farthest reaches of the state. Moore's personal materials cast light on the upper strata of Detroit's society at the height of the Gilded Age and his business records encompass a range of legal activities and reveal the frenetic pace of business and speculation in the years preceding the Great Depression. Political materials and personal writings further reflect some of the most contentious issues of his day, from Free Silver to the public ownership of utilities. This collection will be of value to those interested in the history of law, Democratic politics, mining, and industry as well as the social lives of Michiganians in rural and urban settings. The George William Moore papers are divided into three series: Personal, Moore & Moore, and Associated Businesses.
Subjects:
Democratic Party (Mich.). State Central Committee.; Moore, George William, b. 1847.; Barnes-Hecker Mine Disaster, Mich., 1926.; Iron mines and mining--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.; Law firms--Michigan--Detroit.; Lawyers--Michigan--Detroit.; Mine accidents--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.; Moore & Moore.; Marquette (Mich.); Romulus (Mich.); Upper Peninsula (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Moore, George William, b. 1847.; May, Thomas, 1860-1927.
Contributors:
Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925.; Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.; Couzens, James, 1872-1936.
Genre Terms:
Political cartoons.
- Personal
  The Personal series contains biographical materials, correspondence, financial records, and political writings as well as materials related to George William Moore's estate and numerous family members and associates. These latter materials are of particular interest and include correspondence with William Jennings Bryan, letterpress books detailing his brother Francis M. Moore's business in the Upper Peninsula, and items related to his wife (Katherine De Mill Campau) and her remarriage to Daniel J. Campau (who had been best man at the Moores' nuptials). The financial records are also significant for capturing the wide range of Moore's business interests; although specific information about many of these ventures is not present in the collection, these ledgers document his various investments and involvements.
  - Biographical Materials
    - Clippings, 1914, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Wedding, 1885 (Box 1)
    - Divorce, 1922-1923 (Box 1)
    - Death: obituaries, related correspondence, and will, 1926 (Box 1)
    - Political cartoon (by Thomas May ), undated (Folder 1)
      ("The Moore Plan: Make Believe Public Ownership of Utilities")
    - Miscellaneous, undated, 1903-1904 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - General
      (includes letters received from family and business associates)
      - Undated (Box 1)
      - 1874-1881 (Box 1)
      - 1884-1900 (Box 1)
        (includes letters received from Senator Thomas W. Palmer)
      - 1901-1926 (Box 1)
  - Estate
    - Appointment of Executors, 1927 (Box 1)
    - Barnes-Hecker Mine disaster and negotiations, 1927 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - Trustees, 1935 (Box 1)
      - General (alphabetical file), 1927-1947, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Financial Records
      - Collections, transaction, taxes, and related correspondence, 1929-1944 (Box 1)
      - Expense ledger, 1926-1933 (Box 1)
      - Legacies, settlements, claims, and related correspondence, 1927 (Box 1)
    - Inventory, 1927 (Box 1)
    - Legal documents, 1927-1956 (Box 1)
  - Family members and associates
    - Bryan, William Jennings
      - Clippings, ca. 1900-1925 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, 1904-1925 (Box 1)
      - Poster, undated (Volume 1)
    - Campau, Katherine De Mill (wife) (Box 1)
      - Clippings, 1924-1933 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, 1922-1924 (Box 1)
      - Financial Records
        - Account Balances, 1894-1899, 2 ledgers (Box 1)
        - Investments, 1894-1899, 2 ledgers (Box 1)
      - Photograph, ca. 1885 (Box 1)
    - De Mill, Peter (father-in-law), undated (Box 1)
      (obituary)
    - Hoagland, Katherine Moore (daughter)
      - Biographical materials, 1916-1940 (Box 1)
      - Clippings, ca. 1916-1933 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, 1924-1927 (Box 1)
      - Estate, 1934 (Box 1)
      - Photograph, ca. 1916 (Box 1)
    - Miller, Mary Moore (sister)
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1912 (Box 1)
        - Letterpress book related to Michigan land and mining concerns, 1912-1922 (Box 1)
          (countersigned by George William Moore)
      - Estate
        - Disbursements and transactions, 1926-1944 (Box 1)
        - Inventory, ca. 1921 (Box 1)
        - Last will and testament, 1918 (Box 2)
        - Miller-Moore lawsuit, 1928-1929 (Box 2)
          (related materials located in the correspondence of the Estate of George William Moore)
    - Moore, Frances M. (sister-in-law), 1932 (Box 2)
    - Moore, Francis M. (brother)
      - Correspondence (letterpress books), 1909-1911, 2 volumes (Box 2)
      - Deeds and land contracts
        - Ohio land grant, 1867 (Box 2)
          (signed by President Andrew Johnson)
        - Various, 1870-1907 (Box 2)
      - Last will and testament, 1896, 1912 (Box 2)
    - Moore, George Washington (Father)
      - Clippings, 1906 (Box 2)
      - Legal records, 1859-1875 (Box 2)
    - Moore, George Whitney (business partner), 1915 (Box 2)
    - Moore, George William (nephew)
      - Correspondence (alphabetical file), 1927-1939, 5 folders (Box 2)
      - Michigan Mutual Windstorm Insurance brokerage application, 1933 (Box 2)
      - Policy Register of the Farmers' Mutual Fire Insurance Company of Monroe and Wayne Counties, MI, 1911-1934 (Volume 3)
        (volume 3)
    - Moore, James E. (brother), 1917-1918 (Box 2)
    - Seestadt, Lucie (niece), 1904 (Box 2)
  - Financial records
    - Personal Account Ledgers
      - 1905-1920 (Volume 2)
        (volume 2)
      - 1920-1926 (Box 2)
    - Property deeds and related materials, 1921-1922 (Box 2)
    - Real estate holdings (ledger), 1908-1924 (Box 2)
  - Writings
    - "The American Monetary System" (pamphlet), undated (Box 2)
    - "Suggestions to the Peace Conference" (pamphlet), undated (Box 2)
    - Public Utilities: National and Local (manuscript), undated (Box 2)
    - Other, 1888, 1901 (Box 2)
- Moore & Moore
  The Moore & Moore series encompasses the business and financial records of the partnership between George William and George Whitney Moore. These records include case files, financial records and ledgers, and correspondence in letterpress books and from alphabetical files. These latter items detail the legal work of Moore & Moore as well as its various real estate and business dealings. Of particular interest is a letter written by Moore on 4 November 1926 in which he describes the Barnes-Hecker Mine disaster and references Colonel Frank Hecker, a partner in the venture.
  - Certificate of partnership and of surviving co-partner, 1916 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence
    - Alphabetical File, 1925-1926, 5 folders (Box 3)
      (includes letters from Senator James Couzens and Governor William Comstock)
    - Letterpress Books
      - December 1903-October 1904 (Box 3)
      - October 1904-July 1905 (Box 3)
      - August 1905-March 1906 (Box 3)
      - March 1906-November 1906 (Box 3)
      - November 1906-August 1907 (Box 4)
      - August 1907-March 1908 (Box 4)
      - March 1908-December 1908 (Box 4)
      - December 1908-November 1909 (Box 4)
      - February 1911-April 1912 (Box 4)
      - April 1912-July 1913 (Box 5)
      - July 1913-December 1914 (Box 5)
      - December 1914-March 1916 (Box 5)
      - March 1916-July 1917 (Box 5)
      - August 1917-March 1919 (Box 5)
      - March 1919-October 1920 (Box 6)
      - November 1920-May 1922 (Box 6)
      - June 1926-April 1927 (Box 6)
        (includes correspondence of the Estate of George William Moore)
  - Files
    - Chippewa River Power Plant, 1912-1915 (Box 6)
    - Giegler mortgage petition, 1926 (Box 6)
    - Masrukewitz vs. Moore, 1920 (Box 6)
    - Private Land Claim II, 1891 (Box 6)
      (Campau family property in Grosse Pointe)
    - Stoflet vs. Marker and Egler, 1876 (Box 7)
      (MI Supreme Court case)
    - Stoflet vs. Stoflet, 1925-1926 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1880-1925 (Box 7)
  - Financial Records
    - Ledgers
      - Fees and expenses, 1872-1875 (Box 7)
        (includes Moore & Moore co-partnership agreement)
      - Property tax history and insurance, 1888-1900 (Box 7)
      - Adjustments, cash, profits and loss, etc., 1897-1904 (Box 7)
      - Collection register, 1902-1926 (Box Out volumes)
        (volume 1)
      - Cash (expenses and payments)
        - 1905-1921 (Volume 3)
          (volume 4)
        - 1921-1927 (Volume 5)
          (includes records of the estate of George William Moore)
          (volume 5)
      - General accounts, 1926-1927 (Box 7)
        (includes records of the Estate of George William Moore)
    - Lease agreement (with Daniel J. Campau), 1921 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1886-1923 (Box 7)
  - Other, 1899 (Box 7)
- Associated Businesses
  The Associated Businesses series includes correspondence and ledgers related to enterprises in which Moore was involved (either personally or under the aegis of Moore & Moore). Notable items include Barnes Land Company materials, the Summit Consolidation Silver Mining Company correspondence (a Colorado-based outfit run from the Moore & Moore offices), and the minutes of the Michigan Finance Corporation (an entity established in 1918 to help fund railroad development in the state).
  - Barnes Land Company, ca. 1900-1920 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Finance Corporation, 1919-1920 (Box 7)
  - Sprague Hayes Manufacturing Company, 1919-1921 (Box 7)
  - Summit Consolidation Silver Mining Co., 1881-1882 (Box 7)
  - White Star Portland Cement Company, undated (Box 7)
  - General mining and shipping, 1889, 1908 (Box 7)
Related Material
The Detroit Public Library's Burton Historical Collection has an additional collection of George William Moore's papers that includes records of legal cases handled by the firm of Moore & Moore.